"Ashwagandha, Ginseng, and Maca Root
for Female Sexual Dysfunction"
DHEA supplements
don’t seem to help
with female sexual dysfunction,
but what about
other dietary supplements,
such as the three roots:
ginseng, maca, and ashwagandha?
Ginseng has been suggested,
given its demonstrated efficacy
for male erectile dysfunction
and the fact that it causes
a relaxation response in vitro
to isolated strips
of rabbit vaginal tissue.
But when put to the test
in human studies,
a meta-analysis found
no statistically significant
effect of ginseng
on female sexual dysfunction.
Maca root has been advertised
as Peruvian Viagra.
It’s an important dietary staple
of the indigenous people
of Peru
but appears
to have been overly hyped
as a libido enhancer
based largely on studies
of male rodents.
Yes, maca seems to enhance
the sexual function
of male mice and rats,
but of the two trials
on sexual desire in male humans,
only one showed
a significant benefit,
but it took eight weeks
to show an effect,
which may explain
the negative results
of the second study,
which only lasted two weeks.
A pilot study
without a placebo control
on the management
of sexual dysfunction
induced by SSRIs (due to drugs
like Prozac or Zoloft)
on mostly women
suggested maca may be useful,
but when properly put
to the test in a randomized,
double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial,
it failed to have
a significant effect.
The necessity of placebos
is illustrated
by a maca trial
for infertility.
Maca increased
sperm concentration
by 40 percent!
Yeah, but the placebo
in the study
improved sperm concentration
by 76 percent,
so maca didn’t work after all.
Having placebo controls
is particularly important
for female sexual dysfunction,
since based on studies
of almost 4,000 women,
the placebo effect accounts
for more than two-thirds
of the treatment effect,
similar to the placebo efficacy
of antidepressants.
In contrast, improvement rates
for erectile dysfunction
in men given placebos
are on the order
of 15 percent or less.
The thought is that just the act
of consistent self-monitoring
in female sexual dysfunction
trials,
for example by being asked
to keep a symptom diary,
may improve symptoms
by heightening
the participant’s attention
and awareness
of her own responses
and behaviors,
even in lieu
of an active treatment.
There was one small randomized,
double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial of maca
for sexual dysfunction
in postmenopausal women.
Fourteen women
were randomized
to about 3/4 of a teaspoon
(~4 g) of maca powder
or a placebo powder
every day for six weeks,
after which point they switched
for another six weeks.
While on the real maca,
they reported
significantly fewer symptoms
of sexual dysfunction.
Ashwagandha is a revered herb
of the traditional Indian
Ayurvedic system of medicine.
Its name comes from "ashwa,"
which means horse,
and "gandha,"
which means smell,
because the roots
evidently possess
the "distinctive smell
of a wet horse."
Ashwagandha is used
as a household remedy in India
where it’s been considered
a rasayana, a "rejuvenator,"
or "tonic,"
for thousands of years,
earning it the nickname
of Indian ginseng.
After being fed the root,
rodents thrown
into the deep end
swim twice as long
before sinking
(12 hours versus 6 hours).
Benefits for
physical performance
(including an increase
in aerobic fitness)
have been found in people too.
One study demonstrated evidence
of cognitive benefits as well.
Its Latin name,
Withania somnifera
points to another use
(somnifera means
"sleep-inducer").
A meta-analysis of five
randomized controlled trials
of ashwagandha extracts
found a small
but significant effect
on overall sleep.
What about ashwagandha
and female sexual dysfunction?
Women ages 21 thorough 50
were randomized
to two months
of the estimated equivalent
of three grams
of ashwagandha root powder
and did not have
an increase in sexual desire,
but they did show improvements
over placebo in arousal,
lubrication, orgasm,
and satisfaction,
translating into an additional
quote-unquote
"successful sexual encounter"
by the end of the study.
What are the downsides?
Ashwagandha belongs
to the nightshade family,
which includes some
shady characters like tobacco
and, well,
deadly nightshade.
There have been rare cases
of ashwagandha-linked
liver toxicity reported,
though commercial
herbal supplements
are often mislabeled,
so it’s hard to definitively
attribute certain cases.
However, there have been
several liver injury cases
in which the supplements
have been tested
and found to be
contaminant-free,
suggesting that ashwagandha-
induced liver toxicity
is a real phenomenon,
however rare.
What should we expect
from a plant
known by its other nickname,
poison gooseberry.